<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="Making-image-pyramids.md">

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>Making-image-pyramids.md</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo>libvips</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>libvips</refname>
    <refpurpose>Making-image-pyramids.md</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>


<para>
  libvips includes <literal>vips_dzsave()</literal>, an operation that can build image pyramids compatible with <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_Zoom">DeepZoom</ulink>, Zoomify and <ulink url="https://developers.google.com/maps/">Google Maps</ulink> image viewers. It’s fast and can generate pyramids for large images using only a small amount of memory.
</para>
<para>
  The TIFF writer, <literal>vips_tiffsave()</literal> can also build tiled pyramidal TIFF images, but that’s very simple to use. This page concentrates on the DeepZoom builder.
</para>
<para>
  Run dzsave with no arguments to see a summary:
</para>
<programlisting>
$ vips dzsave
save image to deepzoom file
usage:
   dzsave in filename
where:
   in           - Image to save, input VipsImage
   filename     - Filename to save to, input gchararray
optional arguments:
   basename     - Base name to save to, input gchararray
   layout       - Directory layout, input VipsForeignDzLayout
            default: dz
            allowed: dz, zoomify, google
   suffix       - Filename suffix for tiles, input gchararray
   overlap      - Tile overlap in pixels, input gint
            default: 1
            min: 0, max: 8192
   tile-size    - Tile size in pixels, input gint
            default: 254
            min: 1, max: 8192
   centre       - Center image in tile, input gboolean
            default: false
   depth        - Pyramid depth, input VipsForeignDzDepth
            default: onepixel
            allowed: onepixel, onetile, one
   angle        - Rotate image during save, input VipsAngle
            default: d0
            allowed: d0, d90, d180, d270
   container    - Pyramid container type, input VipsForeignDzContainer
            default: fs
            allowed: fs, zip
   properties   - Write a properties file to the output directory, input
gboolean
            default: false
   compression  - ZIP deflate compression level, input gint
            default: 0
            min: -1, max: 9
   strip        - Strip all metadata from image, input gboolean
            default: false
   background   - Background value, input VipsArrayDouble
operation flags: sequential nocache 
</programlisting>
<para>
  You can also call <literal>vips_dzsave()</literal> from any language with a libvips binding, or by using <literal>.dz</literal> or <literal>.szi</literal> as an output file suffix.
</para>
<refsect3 id="writing-deepzoom-pyramids">
  <title>Writing <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_Zoom">DeepZoom</ulink> pyramids</title>
  <para>
    The <literal>--layout</literal> option sets the basic mode of operation. With no <literal>--layout</literal>, dzsave writes DeepZoom pyramids. For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave huge.tif mydz
</programlisting>
  <para>
    This will create a directory called <literal>mydz_files</literal> containing the image tiles, and write a file called <literal>mydz.dzi</literal> containing the image metadata. 
  </para>
  <para>
    You can use the <literal>--suffix</literal> option to control how tiles are written. For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave huge.tif mydz --suffix .jpg[Q=90]
</programlisting>
  <para>
    will write JPEG tiles with the quality factor set to 90. You can set any format write options you like, see the API docs for <literal>vips_jpegsave()</literal> for details.
  </para>
</refsect3>
<refsect3 id="writing-zoomify-pyramids">
  <title>Writing Zoomify pyramids</title>
  <para>
    Use <literal>--layout zoomify</literal> to put dzsave into zoomify mode. For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave huge.tif myzoom --layout zoomify
</programlisting>
  <para>
    This will create a directory called <literal>myzoom</literal> containing a file called <literal>ImageProperties.xml</literal> with the image metadata in, and a series of directories called <literal>TileGroupn</literal>, each containing 256 image tiles.
  </para>
  <para>
    As with DeepZoom, you can use <literal>--suffix</literal> to set jpeg quality.
  </para>
</refsect3>
<refsect3 id="writing-google-maps-pyramids">
  <title>Writing <ulink url="https://developers.google.com/maps/">Google Maps</ulink> pyramids</title>
  <para>
    Use <literal>--layout google</literal> to write Google maps-style pyramids. These are compatible with the <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/virtualmicroscope/wiki/SlideTiler">NYU Pathology pyramid builder</ulink>. For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave wtc.tif gmapdir --layout google
</programlisting>
  <para>
    Will create a directory called <literal>gmapdir</literal> containing <literal>blank.png</literal>, the file to display for blank tiles, and a set of numbered directories, one for each zoom level. The pyramid can be sparse (blank tiles are not written).
  </para>
  <para>
    As with DeepZoom, you can use <literal>--suffix</literal> to set jpeg quality.
  </para>
  <para>
    Use <literal>--background</literal> to set the background colour. This is the colour displayed for bits of the pyramid not in the image (image edges, for example). By default, the image background is white.
  </para>
  <para>
    Use <literal>--centre</literal> to add a border to the image large enough to centre the image within the lowest resolution tile. By default, images are not centred.
  </para>
  <para>
    For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave wtc.tif gmapdir --layout google --background 0 --centre
</programlisting>
</refsect3>
<refsect3 id="other-options">
  <title>Other options</title>
  <para>
    You can use <literal>--tile-size</literal> and <literal>--overlap</literal> to control how large the tiles are and how they overlap (obviously). They default to the correct values for the selected layout.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can use <literal>--depth</literal> to control how deep the pyramid should be. Possible values are <literal>onepixel</literal>, <literal>onetile</literal> and <literal>one</literal>. <literal>onepixel</literal> means the image is shrunk until it fits within a single pixel. <literal>onetile</literal> means shrink until it fits with a tile. <literal>one</literal> means only write one pyramid layer (the highest resolution one). It defaults to the correct value for the selected layout. <literal>--depth one</literal> is handy for slicing up a large image into tiles (rather than a pyramid).
  </para>
  <para>
    You can use <literal>--angle</literal> to do a 90, 180 or 270 degree rotate of an image during pyramid write.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can use <literal>--container</literal> to set the container type. Normally dzsave will write a tree of directories, but with <literal>--container zip</literal> you’ll get a zip file instead. Use .zip as the directory suffix to turn on zip format automatically:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave wtc.tif mypyr.zip
</programlisting>
  <para>
    to write a zipfile containing the tiles. You can use <literal>.szi</literal> as a suffix to enable zip output as well.
  </para>
  <para>
    Use <literal>--properties</literal> to output an XML file called <literal>vips-properties.xml</literal>. This contains a dump of all the metadata vips has about the image as a set of name-value pairs. It’s handy with openslide image sources.
  </para>
</refsect3>
<refsect3 id="preprocessing-images">
  <title>Preprocessing images</title>
  <para>
    You can use <literal>.dz</literal> as a filename suffix, meaning send the image to <literal>vips_dzsave()</literal>. This means you can write the output of any vips operation to a pyramid. For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips extract_area huge.svs mypy.dz[layout=google] 100 100 10000 10000
</programlisting>
  <para>
    The arguments to <literal>extract_area</literal> are image-in, image-out, left, top, width, height. So this command will cut out a 10,000 by 10,000 pixel area from near the top-left-hand corner of an Aperio slide image, then build a pyramid in Google layout using just those pixels.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you are working from OpenSlide images, you can use the shrink-on-load feature of many of those formats. For example:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
$ vips dzsave CMU-1.mrxs[level=1] x
</programlisting>
  <para>
    Will pull out level 1 (the half-resolution level of an MRXS slide) and make a pyramid from that.
  </para>
</refsect3>
<refsect3 id="troubleshooting">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>
  <para>
    If you are building vips from source you do need to check the summary at the end of configure carefully. You must have the <literal>libgsf-1-dev</literal> package for <literal>vips_dzsave()</literal> to work.
  </para>
</refsect3>


</refentry>
